Music was his passion. Survival was his masterpiece.
The Pianist is a drama, war film directed by Roman Polanski.
The true story of pianist Władysław Szpilman's
experiences in Warsaw during the Nazi occupation.
When the Jews of the city find themselves forced into a ghetto, Szpilman finds work playing in a café; and when his family is deported in
1942, he stays behind, works for a while as a laborer, and eventually goes into hiding in the ruins of the war-torn city.
Władysław 'Władek' Szpilman, played by Adrien Brody.
Captain Wilm Hosenfeld, played by Thomas Kretschmann.
Father, played by Frank Finlay.
Mother, played by Maureen Lipman.
Dorota, played by Emilia Fox.
Henryk Szpilman, played by Ed Stoppard.
The Pianist is a 2002 epic biographical historical drama film produced and directed by
Roman Polanski, with a script by Ronald Harwood, and starring Adrien Brody.
It is based on the autobiographical book The Pianist (1946), a memoir by the
Polish-Jewish pianist, composer and Holocaust survivor Władysław Szpilman.
The film was a co-production by France, the United Kingdom, Germany and Poland.
The Pianist premiered at the 2002 Cannes Film Festival on 24 May 2002, where it won the Palme d'Or, and went into wide release that September; the
film received widespread critical acclaim, with critics lauding Polanski's direction, Brody's performance and Harwood's screenplay.
At the 75th Academy Awards, the film won for Best Director (Polanski), Best Adapted Screenplay (Harwood), and
Best Actor (Brody), and was nominated for four others, including Best Picture (it lost to Chicago).
It also won the BAFTA Award for Best Film and BAFTA Award for Best Direction in 2003, and seven
French Césars, including Best Picture, Best Director, and Best Actor for Brody.
It appeared in BBC's 100 Greatest Films of the 21st Century in 2016.
The film explores themes of concert, nazi,
resistance, warsaw ghetto, polish resistance.
The tone is emotional and thought_provoking.